Finding Aid for Donald E. Hultquist Papers, 1962-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donald E. Hultquist Papers, 1962-1999 1979-1987
Hultquist, Donald E.
1.3 linear ft.
0330 Aa 2
Professor of biochemistry at the University of Michigan. Files related to civic activities and participation in University-wide debates on issues of public policy; include files from work on Citizens' Advisory Committee on Racial Balance and Equal Opportunity in Ann Arbor Schools, 1979; also papers dealing with debate within the University over classified and non-classified research sponsored by U.S. Department of Defense, 1968-1986.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was the gift of Donald E. Hultquist (donor no. 9242 ) and came to the library in 2002.
The collection is open to research.
Donald E. Hultquist is professor emeritus of the Biochemistry Department at the University of Michigan. Dr. Hultquist received his Ph.D. from the University of Rochester in 1962. He joined the Department of Biochemistry at the University of Michigan in 1964 and remained until his retirement in 2000. During his tenure, Professor Hultquist served on numerous committees in the Department of Biology, the Medical School and for the University of Michigan. He ended is career with the Department of Biochemistry as Associate Chair. His research interests included Methemogloblin reduction in normal and abnormal cells, the role of proteases in thyroid maturation and the chemistry of hemes and neme protein. In 1976, Professor Hultquist received the University of Michigan's Distinguished Service and Outstanding Teaching Award. He also received the Japan Society's Promotion of Science Fellowship in 1985.
Professor served two terms on the University Senate Assembly (1980-1983, 1995-1998). He also served on the Research Polices Committee (1980-1985) and was actively involved in the debate over classified and non-classified research at the University of Michigan. He supported the effort to prevent the University from conducting Department of Defense classified and non-classified research that would eventually be used to destroy human life or incapacitate human beings.
As a member of the Ann Arbor community, Professor Hultquist was an advocate for racial balance in the community's public schools. In 1979, He served as coordinator of the Citizens' Racial Advisory Committee on Racial Balance and Educational Opportunities formed by the Ann Arbor Schools administration.
The Donald E. Hultquist papers contain material pertaining to Professor Hultquist's professional and civic activities from 1962-1999, in particular, his work on behalf of racial desegregation in Ann Arbor Schools and his involvement in the University's debate over classified research. The collection is divided into three series: Academic accomplishments; Citizens' Advisory Committee on Racial Balance and Equal Opportunity in Ann Arbor Schools; and Classified Research at the University of Michigan.
Subjects:
Hultquist, Donald E.; Citizen's Advisory Committee on Racial Balance and Educational Opportunities in Ann Arbor Schools.; Military research--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; School integration--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Research.
- Academic Accomplishments
  The first series, Academic Accomplishments, contains Professor Hultquist's curriculum vita and copies of his scientific research papers.
  - Curriculum Vita (Box 1)
  - Published Scientific Papers, 1962-1979 (Box 1)
  - Published Scientific Papers, 1980-1999 (Box 1)
- Citizen's Advisory Committee on Racial Balance and Educational Opportunities in Ann Arbor Schools, 1977-1980
  The second series, Citizens' Advisory Committee on Racial Balance and Equal Opportunity in Ann Arbor Schools, contains information detailing the efforts of the Advisory Committee and the Ann Arbor School Administration, to develop alternative methods for desegregating and to provide equal educational opportunities in the Ann Arbor School system. A majority of the committee's work is found in the reports submitted to the schools' administration.
  - Activities of the Advisory Committee on Racial Balance in Ann Arbor Schools (Box 1)
  - Constituting 1979 Racial Imbalance Committee (Box 1)
  - Reports from Ann Arbor Schools to the Committee, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Outside Information Provided to the Committee (not Ann Arbor Schools), 1977, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Committee Minutes, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Task Force Reports, 1979
    - Task Force on Achievement (Box 1)
    - Community Solutions (Box 1)
    - Housing (Box 1)
    - Resource Allocation and Evaluation (Box 1)
  - Workings of the Committee, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Reports of the Task Forces I-V, 1979 (Box 1)
  - School Administration & School Board, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Reports of the Citizen's Advisory Committee, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Reports of the Citizen's Advisory Committee Appendix, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
- Classified Research at the University of Michigan
  The third series titled, Classified Research at the University of Michigan deals with the debate over classified and non-classified research sponsored by the U.S. Department of Defense at the University of Michigan. During Professor's Hultquist terms in the Senate Assembly he was opposed to the University's involvement in any classified research that would result in the harm or death of human beings. This series represents the formal documents (reports, correspondence, reviews) documenting the involved parties' various opinions.
  - Debate I -- Classified Research at the University of Michigan, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Documents involving University Administration and Regents, 1976, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Reports from the Research Policy Committee (Box 1)
  - Reports and Reviews from other Groups, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
  - Documents from Research Policy Committee, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
  - Involvement of Don Hultquist, 1981-1987 (Box 2)
    (include presentation given by Professor Hultquist on the history of the debate)
  - Input from Individual and Groups, 1982-1986 (Box 2)
  - Senate Assembly Documents, 1972, 1981-1983 1986 (Box 2)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
  - Nuclear Free Zone (proposed amendment to Ann Arbor city charter) (Box 2)